Finding Aid for J. C. Catford papers, 1969-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. C. Catford papers 1969-1985
Catford, J. C. (John Cunnison), 1917-
2.97 GB online
0.3 linear feet
2012026 Aa 2
Professor of linguistics at the University of Michigan from 1964 to 1986; includes eight lectures given by Catford on the occasion of his retirement, handouts from the lectures, a letter supporting Catford's nomination for the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award, an article about Catford in Michigan Today.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
English Language Institute (donor 3349 ) through Alan Pagliere in 2006.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
John ("Ian") Cunnison Catford was born on March 26, 1917 in Edinburgh, Scotland and studied at the University of Edinburgh and the Institut de Phonétic of the University of Paris in the late 1930s. In 1939, he travelled to Athens, Greece to work at the Institute of English Studies and from 1941-1946, he resided in the Middle East, serving with the British Council in Greece, Egypt, and Palestine.
After the long interruption of the Second World War, Catford returned to Britain in 1946 and completed his formal education at the University of London in 1952. He then returned to Scotland and to the University of Edinburgh where he was first research lecturer with The Linguistic Survey of Scotland and then senior lecturer and director of the School of Applied Linguistics.
Joining the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1964, Catford served first as director of the English Language Institute and professor of linguistics. He was active in departmental, college, and University affairs; served a term on SACUA; headed the Laboratory of Communicative Sciences; and on two different occasions assumed the chairmanship of the Department of Linguistics.
Catford's books and articles dealt with all aspects of phonetics, with the theory of translation, and with the application of linguistic knowledge to methods of second language instruction. He was also keenly interested in the languages of the Caucuses and renowned for his ability to pronounce a wide variety of words and linguistic sounds. His expertise was internationally known and led to invitations to Britain, North America and the Near East as well as Uganda, Japan, Hong Kong and the USSR. Catford retired from active faculty status on May 31, 1986 but continued to publish articles and participate in conferences for years afterwards. Catford and his wife, Lotte, had two children, Lorna and Julian; he died of complications from pneumonia on October 6, 2009 in Seattle, Washington.
*From Proceedings of the Board of Regents (1984-1987) pages 711-712
The J. C. Catford papers are significant for insight into the life and career of their creator and also for their information on linguistics, phonetics, and the instruction and acquisition of second languages. In addition to research articles co-authored by Catford, there are video-recordings from a series of lectures he delivered before his retirement from the University of Michigan. The collection consists of two series: Lectures and Written Materials.
Subjects:
Catford, J. C. (John Cunnison), 1917-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Department of Linguistics.; University of Michigan. English Language Institute.; Phonetics.; Linguistics.; Speech.
Genre Terms:
Lectures.; Videocassettes.
- Lectures
  The Lectures series includes video recordings of "The Catford Lectures," a series of eight lectures given by Catford from February to April, 1985 on occasion of his retirement. The following is a brief description of each lecture:
  - V Recordings-Digital Files
    - February 7, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 1: Catford talks about his early life in Scotland and the development of his interest in linguistics as a schoolboy; covers his life through about 1936.
    - February 14, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 2: Catford describes his time as a university student at Edinburgh University and the Institut de Phonétique in the late 1930s.
    - February 21, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 3: Catford begins the lecture by discussing structuralism, then talks about his experience as an instructor of English as a second language at the Institute of English Studies in Athens, Greece from 1939-194. Includes an anecdote about how he became interested in the languages of the Caucasus during this time.
    - March 7, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 4: Catford begins lecturing about the Basic English concept developed by Charles K. Ogden, which Catford taught at the Institute of English Studies in Athens. Catford then discusses his time in the Middle East from 1941-1946, where he resided in or travelled to Egypt, Palestine, Jordan, and Syria while working for the British Council.
    - March 14, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 5: Catford discusses how, after 1946, he returned to Britain, studying under the linguist J.R. Firth at London University in the School of Oriental and African Studies. During this time, he also learned Russian in the School of Slavic and East European Studies.
    - March 28, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 6: Catford talks about his experiences with the Linguistic Survey of Scotland, beginning in 1952.
    - April 4, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 7: Catford describes his tenure, beginning in 1957, as director of University of Edinburgh's School of Applied Linguistics, which was established to provide experienced teachers of English as a second language with a theoretical foundation in instruction.
    - April 18, 1985, .MPEG file
      Lecture 8: Catford continues talking about the School of Applied Linguistics and also discusses how he came to the University of Michigan in 1964 as director of the English Language Institute and professor of linguistics and became involved with the Center for Research in Language and Language Behavior. He also gives criticism of transformational grammar.
  - Video Recordings -- Tape and DVD
    - Lectures 1-8, 8 optical disks DVDs (Box 1)
    - Lectures 1-8, 8 videotapes Mini-DV (Box 1)
      Staff use only
    - Lectures 1-8 (Box 1)
  - Handouts February 7-April 4, 1985 (Box 1)
- Written Materials
  The Written Materials series consists of two research articles on language acquisition and implications for identity as well as a 1985 article from the Michigan Daily ("How to Learn a Language") and a nomination letter from Alan Pagliere, a former student and teaching assistant, to the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Awards Committee in support of recognition for Catford.
  - Letter from Alan Pagliere to Distinguished Faculty Achievement Awards Committee February 18, 1985
  - Michigan Today Article, August 1985 (Vol. 17, No. 2)
  - Research Articles
    - "Grammatical Gender and Gender Identity Development: Cross Cultural and Cross Lingual Implications" 1974, .PDF file
    - "The Role of Personality Variables in Second Language Behavior" 1969, .PDF file
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the English Language Institute (University of Michigan) records held by the Bentley Historical Library.